Hey, Vsauce. Michael here.
Ngocanh_Ailend` Chào Vsauce. Michael đây.
Mimas is one of Saturn's cutest moons.
Mimas là một trong những mặt trăng dễ thương nhất của Sao Thổ.
Its entire surface area is about the same as
Toàn bộ bề mặt của nó có diện tích
Spain but its giant crater makes it look like the
như Tây Ban Nha nhưng những hố khổng lồ của nó
Death Star. And when NASA made a temperature map
khiến nó trông như Death Star. Và khi NASA vẽ bản đồ nhiệt của Mimas
of Mimas, they found that the warmest regions, shown here in yellow,
họ phát hiện ra vùng ấm nhất, ở đây ở phần màu vàng này,
resemble Pac-Man eating the crater
trông như Pac-Man đang ăn miệng núi lửa.
like a dot. I learned about Mimas whilst
Tôi đọc về Mimas trong khi đang lướt mạng
surfing the world wide web like a true internaut.
như một internaut đúng nghĩa.
But the Web and the
Nhưng Web và Internet
Internet are different things. The World Wide Web
là những thứ khác nhau. World Wide Web
and the Internet have names that are similar shapes but they
và Internet có cái tên chỉ những thứ có hình dạng giống nhau (web và net: mạng lưới)
catch different things. And, as we will see,
nhưng chúng bắt những thứ khác nhau. Và như ta sẽ thấy
surfing the world wide web is radical
lướt web là một từ rất đúng và thích hợp.
but it's also apropos. Metaphorically speaking
Nói một cách ẩn dụ thì
the web is pretty wet.
web khá là ướt.
Before the web existed, and before the Internet existed,
Trước khi web tồn tại và trước khi Internet tồn tại,
there were computers but they were big
có máy tính nhưng chúng cồng kềnh và riêng rẽ.
and lonely. They couldn't really talk to one another.
Chúng không thể nói chuyện với nhau được.
I mean, sure, you could connect similar pieces of hardware that spoke similar
Ý tôi là, hẳn rồi, bạn có thể kết nối những phần cứng tương tự nhau
protocols but that was just
dùng chung một giao thức
a network. To connect disparate global machines
nhưng đấy chỉ là một mạng. Để kết nối những chiếc máy khắp nơi trên thế giới tồn tại riêng biệt
you would need a network of networks.
bạn cần một mạng những mạng lưới.
And in the 1960s a bunch of brilliant minds collaborated on just
Và vào năm 1960, rất nhiều những bộ óc tinh hoa
such a thing. Now, at the time, the phone companies weren't very interested
đã hợp tác để tạo ra thứ như vậy. Bây giờ, thời điểm này, những công ty điện thoại không còn thức sự nhận được nhiều hứng thú
and because no single institution could foot the entire responsibility
và bởi vì không 1 tổ chức riêng rẽ nào có thể giải quyết toàn bộ những trách nhiệm
and computing power needed for dedicated lines... Well,
và khả năng tính toán cần thiết cho những đường dây chuyên dụng...
more innovative and efficient methods were used.
vâng, những phương pháp nâng cao hơn và hiệu quả hơn đã được sử dụng.
A system spanning many nations is international.
Một hệ thống bao trùm nhiều quốc gia, là quốc tế.
So, a system spanning many networks
Vậy, một hệ thống bao trùm nhiều mạng
is an Internetwork. It wouldn't be until 1974,
là 1 mạng quốc tế.  Cho đến năm 1974,
in this very document, that the word Internetwork
trong những văn bản, từ mạng quốc tế
would be officially shortened to what we use today - Internet.
mới được rút ngắn thành từ mà chúng ta đang sử dụng bây giờ - Internet.
On October 29th, 1969,
vào ngày 29 tháng 10 năm 1969
exactly 100 days after we first
chính xác là 100 ngày sau khi chúng ta lần đâu tiên
landed on a distant rock across space,
đặt chân đến hòn đá xa ngoài không gian
we first landed a letter on a
chúng ta lần đầu tiên đặt 1 bức thư tại một bàn hình ở khoảng cách xa
distant screen across the Internet. Leonard Kleinrock and a team at UCLA
thông qua Internet.  Leonard Kleinrock  và  nhóm của ông ở  UCLA
decided to send the word
quyết định gửi từ
'login' to a different model of computer at Stanford.
'login' tới một máy tính khác ở Stanford.
They sent the 'L' and it arrived. They sent the 'O'
Họ đã gửi 'L' và bức thư đã được nhận. Họ đã gửi 'O'
and it arrived. And then the system crashed.
và nó cũng đã tới nơi. Và sau đó hệ thống đã bị lỗi.
But still, the first message sent over an Internet
Dù vậy, tin nhắn đầu tiên được gửi đi qua Internet
was a big deal. On a list of technological achievements it would rank
cho đến nay vẫn là 1 thành công lớn. Trong danh sách những thành tựu công nghệ nó được xếp hạng
quite high, even though it was literally
khá cao, mặc dù theo nghĩa đen nó đã
lo... Fast-forward
nhanh-theo
two decades. CERN is working on a lot of different projects with different people
2 thập kỷ. CERN đang hoạt động trên nhiều dự dán với những con người
and technologies
và công nghệ khác  nhau.
to figure out who or what is doing what...
để tìm ra người nào hoặc cái gì làm gì...
You can just look it up on the Internet. But the way information was organized on the internet
Bạn chỉ có thể tìm thấy nó trên Internet. Nhưng cách mà những thông tin được tổ chức trên internet
was illogical. Based on hierarchies,
khá vô lý. Dựa vào phân cấp,
linearly, it was lame. And this annoyed a guy
tuyến tính, Và nó rất khập khiễng. Và nó làm phiền đến 1 người tên là
named Tim Berners-Lee. You see,  you could follow a tree for a really long time
Tim Berners-Lee. Bạn thấy đấy, bạn có thể theo 1 cây trong 1 thời gian dài
only to reach a person or technology involved in some other project
chỉ để đạt tới 1 người hoặc công nghệ  tham gia vào 1 số những dự án khác
and for information on that you have to go back to the beginning and start all
và cho thông tin rằng bạn có phải quay lại vạch xuất phát và bắt đầu
over again.
tất cả 1 lần nữa.
So, in March of 1989, Tim Berners-Lee
Vào tháng 3 năm 1989, Tim Berners-Lee
wrote a powerful paper simply titled "Information management:
đã viết 1 trang giấy với tựa là " quản lý thông tin:
A Proposal." He argued that notes with links,
Một đề xuất. " Anh ấy tranh luận rằng những chú ý với những liên kết,
like references, between them is far more useful than a
giống như tài liệu tham khảo, giữa chúng là hữu ích hơn nhiều so với
fixed hierarchical system. Instead of trees,
hệ thống phân cấp cố định. Thay vì những cây,
Berners-Lee was proposing a web.
Berners-Lee đã hướng tới 1 mạng lưới.
Webbed systems that connect documents in nonlinear ways already existed.
Hệ thống mạng liên kết nhưng văn bản trong cách phi tuyến đang tồn tại.
They were called hypertext. But Tim Berners-Lee
Chúng được gọi là siêu văn bản. Nhưng Tim Berners-Lee
officiated the marriage of hypertext webs and the Internet
đã chủ trì sự kết hợp của các trang siêu văn bản và Internet
to produce a web that was worldwide. It was the vast connected logical and
để tạo nên 1 trang mạng trên phạm vi toàn thế giới. Nó là một sự kết hợp logic rộng lớn và
useful partnership needed to make the Internet the most quickly adopted
quan hệ hữu ích cần thiết để làm cho Internet
form of communication in our species' history.
thành 1 phương thức giao tiếp nhanh nhất trong lịch sử loài người.
The Internet connects participants,
Internet kết nối những người tham gia,
the web connects information. Specifically
và những trang mạng kết nối thông tin .
hypertext documents accessed via the Internet.
Đặc biệt là nhưng siêu văn bản được truy cập thông qua Internet.
You can see the computer Tim Berners-Lee created the world wide web with
Bạn có thể thấy cái máy tính mà Tim Berners-Lee đã dùng để tạo nên 1 trang mạng phạm vi toàn cầu
in the London Science Museum. Twenty-five years ago
ở bào tàng khoa học London. Hai mươi lăm năm trước
if you had unplugged this computer you would have literally shut down
nếu bạn cắm điện vào máy tính này bạn sẽ hoàn toàn tắt
the entire web. The first website
toàn bộ trang mạng. Website đầu tiên là info.cern.ch.
was info.cern.ch. Today it provides a simulator that allows you to
Ngày nay nó cung cấp 1 thiết bị mô hình hóa cho phép bạn
view the web
xem được trang
as it appeared as a baby. We've come
giống như lúc nó mới được xuất hiện.
a long way since this. If you really want your mind blown,
chúng ta đã đi được 1 chặng đường dài kể từ đây. Nếu bạn thực sự muốn tâm trí của bạn được thôi bay,
check out Onesecond[.designly.com] on the web. You can see how many
kiểm tra Onesecond[.designly.com] trên trang mạng. Bạn có thể thấy có bao nhiêu
Facebook likes, Tweets and even e-mails are sent every second
lượng like Facebook, lượng Tweets và thậm chí cả thư điện tử được gửi mỗi giâi
and how many have been sent since you first opened the page.
Và có bao nhiêu cái đã được gửi đên từ khi bạn mở trang đó ra lần đầu tiên.
Isaac Asimov once said that Earth should have been named
Isaac Asimov  đã từng có lần nói rằng Trái đất đã nên được gọi là
ocean because the sea is its dominant
đại dương bởi vì biển cả là
feature. Our oceans are vast
đặc điểm nổi bật của trái đất. Những đại dương của chúng ta bao la
and dangerous and deep and mysterious. So, it's no mystery that when people needed
nguy hiểm, sâu sắc và bí ẩn. Vì vậy, không có gì bí ẩn khi con người cần
a metaphor to describe the Internet
một phép ẩn dụ để mô tả về Internet và
and the seemingly endless and often uncharted
và những trang web của các siêu văn bản được vận chuyển thường là vô tận và không được biết đến,
web of hypertext it delivered, they ran for the sea.
chúng hoạt động cho đại dương.
We surf the web, navigating
chúng ta lướt web, luồng điều hướng dữ liệu.
streams of data. There are pirates and floods and phishing.
Ở đây có cả cướp biển, lũ lụt và cả lừa đảo.
Even blogs and vlogs have their linguistic origins
Ngay cả blog và vlog đều có nguồn gốc ngôn ngữ của riêng nó
in logs - records originally kept by captains at sea.
ở trong các ban ghi: những ban gi gốc được giữ bởi những thuyền trưởng ngoài đại dương.
Like liquid water, the web is a phenomenal solvent.
như nước lỏng, trang web là 1 dung môi phi thường
It makes material widely accessible and available.
Nó làm cho những vật liệu có thể tiếp cận rộng rãi và luôn có sẵn.
It has been estimated that every web page is an average
Ước tính rằng mỗi 1 trang web
of only 19 clicks away from every
là trung bình của mỗi 19 cái kích chuột cách xa
other web page. Like our oceans,
mỗi trang web khác. Giống như đại dương của chúng ta,
the web is really just one global
trang web thực sự là 1 đại dương toàn cầu.
sea. And like our oceans, the web
Và giống như những đại dương của chúng ta, trang Web
is an ecosystem we need to be careful to protect.
là  1 hệ thống sinh thái chúng ta cần chăm sóc bảo vệ.
It is flexible and flowing, and as we are finding out,
Nó rất linh hoạt và có tính chảy, và như chúng ta đang tìm kiếm,
the web, like liquid water, is something you can see yourself in.
trang web, giống như nước lỏng, là thứ gì đó mà bạn có thể thấy bản thân mình trong đó.
In the 1990s, Douglas Rushkoff coined the term
Vào những năm 1990, Douglas Rushkoff đặt ra thuât ngữ
screenagers to describe a generation that for the first time ever was growing
bộ lọc để mô tả 1 thế hệ cho lần đầu tiên phát triển
up to think that images
để nghĩ rằng những hình ảnh
on screens weren't just something to passively stare at,
trên màn hình không phải chỉ là thứ gì đó để nhìn chằm chằm vào,
but, instead, were something to be manipulated.
nhưng, thay vào đó, nó là 1 thứ gì đó để điều khiển và thao tác.
Well, today it's even more extreme.
Vâng, ngay nay nó thậm chí còn cực hạn hơn.
The tools and connectivity, provided by the Web, allow us to think
Những công cụ và hoạt động kết nối,  cung cấp bởi trang web, cho phép chúng ta nghĩ về
of images on screens not just as things to manipulate
những hình ảnh trêm màm hình không chỉ là những thứ để điều khiển, thao tác
but as things to project our own identities onto.
mà còn là thứ để thực hiện những dự án nhận dạng của chúng ta lên đó.
Not everyone who does this is a professional storyteller
Không phải tất cả mọi người đều dùng nó như một người kể chyện
or acclaimed poet or coherent.
một nhà thơ hoặc liên kết chuyên nghiệp.
But, content aside, hyperlinked webs of human expression are incredibly rich enviroments
nhưng, nội dung bên cạnh,  các mạng lưới liên kết những biểu hiện của con người là một môi trường vô cùng phong phú
and they exercise the brain, more so than books?
và họ rèn liệu bộ não, nhiều hơn bằng những quyển sách?
Well, for the sake of argument,
Vâng, vì lợi ích của những đối số,
let's read from "Everything Bad is Good for You,"
hãy đọc "mọi thứ tồi tệ là tốt cho bạn",
a book by Steven Johnson. Now, in this passage
1 quyển sách của  Steven Johnson. Ngày nay, trong đoạn văn này
he imagines a world in which books were invented
anh ta  tưởng tượng ra một thế giới ở trong cuốn sách này đã được phát minh
after video games and the World Wide Web.
sau video game  và  mạng toàn cầu.
Kids everywhere are starting to read these new fangled
Những đứa trẻ ở khắp mọi nơi bắt đầu đọc  những cuốn sách mới
books and teachers and parents are concerned. He imagines
phụ huynh và giáo viên cũng quan tâm đến. Anh ta tưởng tượng
they might say something like this:
họ có thể nói những thứ giống như:
"Perhaps the most dangerous property of these books
" Có thể  điểm nguy hiểm nhất của những cuốn sách này
is the fact that they follow a fixed linear path.
là sự thật rằng họ  đang đi theo một đường thẳng cố định.
You can't control their narratives in any fashion. You simply sit back
Bạn không thể điều khiển những thuyết minh của chúng trong bất cứ kiểu cách nào. Bạn cơ bản là ngồi xuống và
and have the story dictated to you.
và có câu chuyện bắt nguồn từ bạn.
For those of us raised on interactive narratives, this property may seem
Đối với những người trong chúng ta đưa ra những câu chuyện tương tác,
astonishing. Why would anyone want to embark on an adventure
astonishing. Why would anyone want to embark on an adventure
utterly choreographed by another person?
utterly choreographed by another person?
But today's generation embarks on such adventures
But today's generation embarks on such adventures
millions of times a day. Reading is not an
millions of times a day. Reading is not an
active participatory process, it's a submissive one.
active participatory process, it's a submissive one.
The book readers of the younger generation are learning
The book readers of the younger generation are learning
to follow the plot instead of learning to lead."
to follow the plot instead of learning to lead."
Interesting. But you might be thinking, come on,
Interesting. But you might be thinking, come on,
Michael, you can't set content aside that easily.
Michael, you can't set content aside that easily.
What about all the dumb and superficial stuff the web propagates?
What about all the dumb and superficial stuff the web propagates?
I mean, surely a lot of it is just completely useless. We're humans, after all, we should
I mean, surely a lot of it is just completely useless. We're humans, after all, we should
be valuing reason. Maybe.
be valuing reason. Maybe.
But is that really what makes us special? As Unamuno said,
But is that really what makes us special? As Unamuno said,
"more often I have seen a cat reason
"more often I have seen a cat reason
than laugh or weep. Perhaps it weeps or laughs
than laugh or weep. Perhaps it weeps or laughs
inwardly. But then perhaps, also inwardly, a crab resolves equations
inwardly. But then perhaps, also inwardly, a crab resolves equations
of the second degree." What if cheap laughs and sappy poems and gossip and
of the second degree." What if cheap laughs and sappy poems and gossip and
whining and drama and selfies really are
whining and drama and selfies really are
the most human thing the web has allowed us to do?
the most human thing the web has allowed us to do?
That's deep. But not as deep as the Deep Web,
That's deep. But not as deep as the Deep Web,
the hidden web. The part of the web invisible
the hidden web. The part of the web invisible
to search engines. Now, most of this stuff is innocuous content hidden behind pay
to search engines. Now, most of this stuff is innocuous content hidden behind pay
walls or password protection
walls or password protection
or dynamically created web pages. But we haven't
or dynamically created web pages. But we haven't
even indexed this stuff. And it's not 1% of the web,
even indexed this stuff. And it's not 1% of the web,
it's not 10%. It's 80%
it's not 10%. It's 80%
of the entire World Wide Web.
of the entire World Wide Web.
The web is a deep ocean
The web is a deep ocean
and we are frantically making waves in it. For instance, take a look at real time
and we are frantically making waves in it. For instance, take a look at real time
emoji usage on Twitter and say a few words of encouragement to be
emoji usage on Twitter and say a few words of encouragement to be
least popular emoji. We are also exploring the web
least popular emoji. We are also exploring the web
frantically. It's an entirely new frontier. Every single day
frantically. It's an entirely new frontier. Every single day
Google receives 500 million search queries
Google receives 500 million search queries
it has never been asked before.
it has never been asked before.
Where will all of this exploration lead?
Where will all of this exploration lead?
Who knows? But to go back to our metaphor, the very same suits we built to explore
Who knows? But to go back to our metaphor, the very same suits we built to explore
the depths of the ocean
the depths of the ocean
inspired and enabled the suits we would later use
inspired and enabled the suits we would later use
to go beyond Earth. So, keep exploring,
to go beyond Earth. So, keep exploring,
keep surfing.
keep surfing.
And as always,
And as always,
thanks for watching.
thanks for watching.